# Yue Shi Ph.D.'s CV

Yue Shi Ph.D.

2023-12-11

# Aside



#### Download a PDF of this CV

# Contact

- Omak, WA
- Gmail
- Twitter
- GitHub
- LinkedIn

# Skills

R/RStudio

Quarto/R Markdown

Bash

Git/GitHub

GitHub Actions

Snakemake

ChatGPT/Code Interpreter

NGS Analyses

# Disclaimer

Made with the R package **pagedown**.

The source code is available on github.com/melodysyue/CV\_YS.

Last updated on 2023-12-11.

# Main

# Yue Shi Ph.D.

I am a highly accomplished bioinformatician with extensive academic experience in developing and executing complex DNA/RNA research projects. My expertise in bioinformatics and data science is demonstrated through a strong publication record in genomics with lead authorship, presentations at prestigious conferences, and my role as a peer reviewer for several respected academic journals. As a bioinformatics scientist, I am interested in all aspects of genomics and bioinformatics, with a particular focus on evolution, liquid biopsies, interpretable machine learning, and the development of automated, reproducible NGS workflows.

#### Education

#### Ph.D., Biology

University of Washington Seattle, WA 2019

# M.S., Ecology

Ocean University of China Qingdao, China 2013

# **B.S.**, Biological Sciences

Ocean University of China Qingdao, China 2010

# Research Experience

#### Scientist I

Department of Human Oncology, University of Wisconsin - Madison

Remote

Current - 2022

- Optimized a pan-cancer targeted DNA sequencing panel.
- Developed bioinformatics pipelines to call somatic mutations and copy number alterations using circulating cell-free DNA.
- Characterized the features of tumor-derived fragments in cell-free DNA.
- Identified novel targets for cancer treatment development by utilizing machine learning and big data mining.
- Conducted survival analyses and estimated circulating tumor DNA fractions for clinical trials.
- Automated routine tasks for NGS data preprocessing and analysis, specifically for RNA-seq and targeted DNA-seq.
- Mentored MD/PhD students on data science projects.

#### Postdoctoral Fellow

College of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, University of Alaska Fairbanks

Remote

2022 - 2020

- Developed a bioinformatics pipeline to detect structural variants.
- Conducted genome scan analyses within a comparative genomics framework.
- Developed SNP panels to improve the resolution of population structure for fisheries management.
- Developed a bioinformatics pipeline to estimate the number of contributing individuals in DNA mixture samples.

#### Postdoctoral Research Scientist

College of Natural Resources, University of Wisconsin - Stevens Point

Remote

2020 - 2019

- Conducted reduced-representation sequencing library preparation for approximately 2,900 samples.
- Developed normalization protocols using the OT-2 liquid handling robot.
- Trained master's students in DNA metabarcoding bioinformatics pipelines.

#### Graduate Research Assistant

Department of Biology, University of Washington

Seattle, WA

2019 - 2012

• Enhanced the laboratory's high-throughput sequencing capacity by establishing experimental design guidelines, optimizing library preparation protocols, managing reference databases, and setting up bioinformatics pipelines for amplicon sequencing data.

#### **Project Consultant**

BIOFAB, University of Washington

Seattle, WA

2017 - 2016

- Conducted presentations to promote BIOFAB's automated workflows and attract new clients.
- Designed and oversaw molecular cloning projects for clients.
- Gathered feedback from clients and collaborated with team members to incorporate new features into the Aquarium software.

# **Selected Publications**

For a comprehensive list of publications, please visit my ORCID profile

#### Fragmentomic analysis of circulating tumor DNA targeted cancer panels

Annals of Oncology. 10.1016/j.annonc.2023.06.001

N/A

2023

• Kyle T. Helzer, Marina Sharifi, Jamie M. Sperger, Yue Shi, et al.

Conserved islands of divergence associated with adaptive variation in sockeye salmon are maintained by multiple mechanisms

 $\begin{tabular}{ll} Molecular Ecology. & 00, 1-21. & 10.1111/mec.1712600 \\ N/A \end{tabular}$ 

• Peter T. Euclide, Wesley A. Larson, Yue Shi, et al.

Towards absolute abundance for conservation applications: estimating the number of contributors via microhaplotype genotyping of mixed-DNA samples

Molecular Ecology Resources. 00: 1-13. 10.1111/1755-0998.13816 N/A 2023

• Yue Shi, Cory M. Dick, Kirby Karpan, et al.

Gene flow influences the genomic architecture of local adaptation in six riverine fish species

Molecular Ecology (FROM THE COVER). 32: 1549-1566. 10.1111/mec.16317 N/A

2023

2022

2023

• Yue Shi, Kristen L. Bouska, Garrett J. McKinney, et al.

High-density genomic data reveal fine-scale population structure and pronounced islands of adaptive divergence in lake whitefish (*Coregonus clupeaformis*) from Lake Michigan

Evolutionary Applications. 15: 1776-1797. 10.1111/eva.13475 N/A 2022

• Yue Shi, Jared J. Homola, Peter T. Euclide, et al.

A chromosomal inversion may facilitate adaptation despite periodic gene flow in a freshwater fish

Ecology and Evolution. 12: e8898. 10.1002/ece3.8898  $\rm N/A$ 

• Matt J. Thorstensen, Peter T. Euclide, Jennifer D. Jeffrey, Yue Shi, et al.

Prey partitioning between sympatric wild carnivores revealed by DNA metabarcoding: a case study on wolf (*Canis lupus*) and coyote (*Canis latrans*) in northeastern Washington

Conservation Genetics. 22: 293-305. 10.1007/s10592-021-01337-2 N/A 2021

• Yue Shi, Yves Hoareau, Ellen M. Reese, et al.

Shift of maternal gut microbiota of Tibetan Antelope (Pantholops hodgsonii) during the periparturition period

Current Microbiology. 78: 727-738. 10.1007/s00284-020-02339-y N/A 2021

• Yue Shi, Zi-Yan Miao, Jian-Ping Su, et al.

 ${
m eDNA}$  metabarcoding outperforms traditional fisheries sampling and reveals fine-scale heterogeneity in a temperate freshwater lake

Environmental DNA. 3: 912-929. 10.1002/edn3.197 N/A

2021

• Rebecca R. Gehri, Wesley A. Larson, Kristen Gruenthal, Nicholas M. Sard, Yue Shi

# **Academic Services**

# Peer Reviewer

N/A

N/A

N/A

- Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B
- Molecular Ecology
- JCI Insight
- PeerJ
- Journal of Mammalogy
- Frontiers in Marine Science
- Current Microbiology

# Conference Participation

# Oral Presentation

N/A

N/A

N/A

- 151th American Fisheries Society (AFS) Annual Meeting
- 150th AFS Annual Meeting
- 47th Annual Alaska Chapter AFS Meeting
- 2018 North American Congress for Conservation Biology (NACCB)
- 2018 University of Washington (UW) Scholar's Studio
- 2016 3rd Conservation Biology Forum

#### Poster Presentation

N/A

N/A

N/A

• 2018 Sigma Xi Annual Meeting - Big Data Symposium

#### Attendee

N/A

N/A

N/A

- 2023 Hormone-Dependent Cancers Conference, Gorden Research Conference
- 2023 NCI Cancer Diagnosis Program Workshop: ctDNA in Cancer Treatment and Clinical Care

# Fellowships and Awards

# Fellows and Awards

N/A

N/A

N/A

- 2018 Washington Research Foundation Benjamin Hall Fellowship
- 2018 UW Biostatistics Summer Institute Scholarship
- 2017 Riddiford-Truman Award
- 2016 Chester Fritz and Boeing International Fellowship for Research/Study
- 2015 Wingfield-Ramenofsky Award
- 2012 Hall International Fellowship

# Travel Awards

N/A

N/A

N/A

- 2021 AFS Genetics Section Postdoc Travel Award
- 2018 UW Biology Graduate Student Travel Grant
- $\bullet\,$  2018 Graduate and Professional Student Senate Travel Grant
- 2018 NACCB Student Travel Award